if you're insured by manual life the
company's new deal with lbla means you
might have to switches if you need
coverage for specialty medications some
drug policy experts and pharmacists say
this model could negatively impact
customers they may go to their Pharmacy
that they regularly go to and find out
that they have to switch pharmacies or
go somewhere else it could be especially
concerning for patients that live in
rural areas what if your closest
pharmacy is not one of the pharmacies
that allows you to get this so which
specialty drugs will be affected by this
agreement at this point we don't know
exactly which one we've asked manual for
that list but they didn't release it to
us in response they told us that the
change does not impact the vast majority
of our members who have not been
prescribed specialty drugs what we do
know is there are around 260 medications
listed under the insurance company's
specialty drug Care Program these treat
a variety of serious or life-threatening
conditions here are a few of them pause
to read the full list man life says
those kinds of drugs make up less than
1% of its prescription claims but they
make up almost a third of toal Total
Drug spending in Canada because those
medications are some of the most
expensive on the market we're slowly
moving towards the American model where
it's all going to be just high volume
pill factories this kind of deal between
manual life and labla is known as a
preferred Pharmacy Network Arrangement
Which is popular in the US that model is
gaining traction across Canada except in
Quebec where it's banned entirely some
health policy experts say these deals
make sense for companies because it's
profitable they allow insurance
companies to keep costs low and at the
same time they give rebates to the
pharmacies a pharmaceutical policy
expert at Carlton University called
these kinds of deals Shady while an
economist we spoke to said these kinds
of deals are becoming more common in
Canada because they can be costeffective
manual life has identified that they're
basically able to get a better deal by
just going to a single provider when
they get that better deal the idea is
they should be passing on the savings to
their insured customers a manual life
spokesperson says the agreement with
labla will provide more options for
group benefit members and that customers
can have the drugs delivered to their
homes but some independent pharmacists
are concerned that the deal will be a
blow to their business in a country that
already has a problem with lack of
competition across sectors if they're
left out of being able to sign these
larger deals how does this affect their
business model and how does it make it
viable for them to remain open